<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Christians hope. A sermon preached at the solemn funerals, of William Christmas, Esq; in the Church of St. Michael Bassishaw, London, Decemb. 16. 1652. By Phil. Edelen, B.D.</title>
            <author>Edelen, Philip, d. 1657.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 67KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A82833</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867784</idno>
  <idno type="VID">120110</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248501680</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing E159</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1235_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208865</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867784</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99867784e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A82833)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 120110)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 170:E1235[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Christians hope. A sermon preached at the solemn funerals, of William Christmas, Esq; in the Church of St. Michael Bassishaw, London, Decemb. 16. 1652. By Phil. Edelen, B.D.</title>
                  <author>Edelen, Philip, d. 1657.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. Thrale, in S. Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.DC.LIII [1653]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "March 28"; the last 'I' in imprint date is crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Christmas, William, d. 1652.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Funeral sermons --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:120110:1"/>
            <p>The Christians Hope.</p>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED At the Solemn Funerals, of <hi>William Christmas,</hi> Esq in the Church of S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>. <hi>Michael Bassishaw,</hi> Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, <hi>Decemb.</hi> 16. 1652.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Phil. Edelen,</hi> B. D.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Thrale,</hi> in S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. <hi>M. DC. LIII.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:120110:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:120110:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>1 COR. 15. 19.</bibl>
               <q>If in this life only we have hope in Christ, we are of all men most mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serable.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Resurrection of the dead, is a riddle in nature, and a paradox to reason; but an undoubted Article of the Christian faith. <hi>If a man die, shall he live again?</hi> saith <hi>Job;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 14. 14</note> that is, in this world, or by the ordinary course of nature, he shall not, he cannot live againe. Death is a privation of life, and that, <hi>from the privation to the habit, there is no returning:</hi> it goes for a maxim amongst Philosophers, and is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently <note place="margin">A privati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one ad ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitum non datur re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gressus. Plin. lib. 10. c. 2.</note> true, according to the course and power of meer natural causes. That of the long-liv'd Arabian bird, the <hi>Phoenix,</hi> towards her end, making her nest (as it were her death-bed) of spices, which are said to be set on fire by the Sun-beams; and out of her ashes, a worm, and from that worm, a new <hi>Phoenix</hi> to be produced, may well go among vulgar errours (which cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulous <note place="margin">Dr. Brown</note> ignorance and common reception have made currant) and may rhetorically serve for a <note place="margin">Ambr. Hexam. l. 5. cap. 23.</note>
               <hi>symbolical</hi> allusion, but no sound argument, of the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:120110:3"/> Resurrection. Resurrection, (as Creation) is <note place="margin">Tertul. de Resur. car. cap. 13. 2 Cor. 1. 9. John. 11. 45.</note> an act of Omnipotency, an argument of <hi>Christs Deity,</hi> in matter of fact; a work beyond the sphere of Natures activity, and an object of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine faith. One of the greatest masters of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losophie; who saw as far by the dim Moon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shine of natural reason, as any man since his daies (unlesse by having that advantage, which a Dwarfe may have, by standing on a Giants shoulders) could see and say no farther then this, That <hi>of nothing, nothing can be made.</hi> He knew not the difference betwixt <hi>making,</hi> and <note place="margin">Ex nihilo, nihil fit.</note>
               <hi>creating;</hi> To make something of something, is a production natural or artificial, as of an egge, a bird; of a tree, an image: but to bring some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing out of nothing, is supernatural; meerly the finger of <hi>God,</hi> and fals under the notion of faith. And as the creation of things, is an <note place="margin">Heb. 11. 3.</note> omnipotent act, in bringing light out of darkness at the first; so is Redemption, and (the blest issue of it) Regeneration (which is <hi>our new creation)</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5. 17</note>
               <hi>out of the darknesse of ignorance, bringing us to the light of the knowledge of Jesus Christ;</hi> which <note place="margin">2 Cor. 4. 6.</note> is called <hi>the first Resurrection,</hi> Rev. 20. and is the <note place="margin">Rev. 20. 6.</note> raising of the soul, from the corruption of sin, as the second resurrection shall be, the raising of the body, from the corruption of the grave: The one is the act, of a merciful power; the other, of a powerful mercy, and both Gods. That which fals under the Apostles argument at large in this chapter; and our present discourse, is the Resurrection of the body; a grand truth, which the Sadduces denied, the Epicures laughed at, <note place="margin">Luke 20. Acts 17. 23.</note> Profane men tremble at, but good Christians be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, and believing rejoyce in, and rejoycing
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:120110:3"/> desire, and desiring hope and long for; knowing and saying with our Apostle, <hi>If in this life only we have hope in Christ, we are of all men most mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which words, at the first view, present us with these two parts; first, a supposition, and secondly, a conclusion. A supposition, in the first words, <hi>If in this life only we have hope in Christ.</hi> A conclusion in the rest, <hi>we are</hi> (then) <hi>of all men most miserable.</hi> A supposition of a thing very untrue; <hi>Christians to have their hope in Christ, in this life only.</hi> A conclusion of a thing very unjust and unreasonable, <hi>Christians to be of all men most miserable:</hi> But the best is, the first is not a position, but a supposition, or a position (perhaps) of the Sadduces, but a supposition only of the Apostles, which he gives, but grants not, <hi>si nisi non esset;</hi> If it were not for if, Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians were but in a sad case. As to the conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, the consequent is very unjust, that the ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of the best master, should have the worst wages <hi>(absit)</hi> God forbid; that such as have led a strict, mortified and righteous life; yea, and have laid down their pretious lives, for the testimony of Jesus; that they should (like, <hi>mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyres stultae philosophiae)</hi> have no better, no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hopes, then here, and now, where they neither found, nor expected, nor were ever pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised better usage, then reproach, poverty, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secution and the crosse: A consequent [I say] very unjust, yet the consequence or inference, <note place="margin">Mat. 16. 24 Mar. 10. 30 Joh. 16. 33</note> very just and necessary, upon the hypothesis, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which it depends and from whence it argues, as in all connex axioms be the parts (one or both) simply and singly true or false; the inference is
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:120110:4"/> mainly looked at, and that holds strongly here—If—Then. <hi>If in this life only we have hope in Christ,</hi> we are (Then) (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, an <hi>enallage</hi> of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, frequent in the Scriptures, the comparative, <note place="margin">Bezae an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not. in lo.</note> for the superlative) more miserable then any, or most miserable of all men. The design of the Apostle, in his way of arguing all along, is <hi>(adversarium ducere ad absurdum)</hi> by just and due inferences, from the Tenet his Adversarie holds, to bring him thereby necessarily to grant (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) something absurd or ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous. <hi>If there be no resurrection of the dead, then is not Christ risen,</hi> vers. 13. which is plainly against evidence of fact and sense: <hi>Then is our preaching vain, and your faith also vain,</hi> vers. 14. <hi>Then are we false witnesses of God,</hi> vers. 15. <hi>Then you are yet in your sins,</hi> vers. 17. <hi>and the Saints de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted (in this hope) perished,</hi> vers. 18. <hi>Then the baptizing over the dead is in vain,</hi> vers. 29. <hi>Then all the reproaches, dangers &amp; sufferings of Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans even to death, are all in vain,</hi> vers. 30, 32. and in the Text, <hi>Then Christians have their hopes in this life only,</hi> and <hi>then are of all men most mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now upon a second view, having taken off the veil, not so much from the words as from the mind of the hearers, we find the sence quite other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, then the sound of the words, and what is affirmative, upon the supposition, is negative, upon the disquisition, both the antecedent and the consequent; that is, <hi>Christians have not their hope in Christ in this life only: Christians are not of all men most miserable;</hi> and so by a retorted argument (as it were by a back-blow) it implies,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:120110:4"/> that therefore, there must be surely a Resurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the dead. Thus we have looked upon the text, as upon a <hi>fist or hand closed together,</hi> as upon <hi>a rose in the bud:</hi> now we will <hi>blow out this bud into its leaves, stretch out this hand into so many fingers,</hi> in what is exprest or implied, in six pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions. First, <hi>Christians have their hope.</hi> Secondly, <hi>Christians have their hope in Christ.</hi> Thirdly, <hi>Christians have their hope in Christ in this life.</hi> Fourthly, <hi>Christians have their hope in Christ, but not in this life only.</hi> Fiftly, <hi>If Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians had their hopes in Christ, in this life only, they were then of all men most miserable.</hi> Lastly, <hi>Christians, in that they have their hope, and that in Christ, and that in this life, and not in this life only, are not of all men most miserable;</hi> nay, <hi>[con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sideratis considerandis]</hi> upon the whole matter, <hi>are of all men most happy;</hi> and in the compleat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereof, in the shutting up of all, at the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surrection it will appear so. Thus you see the tide runs in upon us, and every part gains of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and swels higher and higher; like <hi>the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in</hi> Ezekiel, <hi>from the ankles to the knees, and</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 4<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <hi>from the knees to the loins, and from the loins to the neck;</hi> and so over head and ears that we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not wade, but must swim through them. Thus I have opened the hand, and stretched it into five particulars, as so many fingers; yea, into six, as many as were the fingers of the <hi>Giant of Gath,</hi> upon each hand six: I must not omit one, lest <note place="margin">2 Sam. 21. 20.</note> some accurate hearer should take notice of it, <hi>as the midwife tied a scarled thred upon the hand of</hi> Pharez, <hi>when he put it forth and drew it in again,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 38. 28.</note>
               <hi>Gen.</hi> 38. Therefore I shall take leave to run through them all; on such as are implyed only,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:120110:5"/> I shall only touch and go, as by the by: on such as are chiefly intended, I shall insist longer, as upon the main; with Gods assistance and your good attention, which I humbly beg: For I see I have cut out as much work, as would require a far better work-man then I am, and more time, then can be reasonably asked or allowed me to do it in: Help me, I beseech you, <hi>Men, brethren and fathers,</hi> help me by your prayers, and by your pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience; your patience shall make my task easier to me, and make the time seem shorter unto you, and now the <hi>good Lord</hi> prosper it in all our hands. I begin with the first.</p>
            <p>Christians have hope: <hi>Faith, hope, and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>1</label> are the <hi>three Theological vertues,</hi> daughters <note place="margin">1 Cor. 13. 13.</note> of one mother, or hand-maides of one mistrisse, which is Divine <hi>Truth:</hi> what <hi>Truth</hi> propoundeth or promiseth, <hi>Faith</hi> believeth, <hi>Love</hi> embraceth, &amp; <hi>Hope</hi> waiteth for; so that <hi>hope is the expectation of some good thing, that is possible and future.</hi> There are <hi>three things</hi> requisite to make up the object of a regular and discreet hope, that it be something; 1. <hi>good, 2. possible, and 3. future.</hi> First, that it be <hi>good,</hi> for whatsoever presents it self as evil (either, <hi>corruptivè</hi> or <hi>contristativè,</hi> as we di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinguish it, into the evil of sin, or of sufferings) the <hi>soul</hi> naturally abominates and avoids it, if that evil be present, <hi>grief</hi> undertakes it; if fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <hi>fear:</hi> It must be <hi>good</hi> then which the soul enlargeth it self unto and makes towards. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this good must be <hi>future,</hi> for if it be present good, <hi>joy</hi> entertains it; but if it be <hi>future,</hi> it fals under the jurisdiction and office of <hi>hope.</hi> Thirdly, it must be <hi>possible,</hi> which possibility is a <hi>conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:120110:5"/> or proportion,</hi> betwixt the end or the thing hoped for, and the means tending to that end: and if no such proportion be apprehensible, this seeming impossibility discourages and balkes hope, which gives over the chase or pursuit, and causes the soul to shrink and shrivel up and dwindle into despaire. Fourthly, <hi>Aquinas</hi> adds <note place="margin">Aqui. 12. q. 40. 1. 0.</note> another qualification of the object of hope; that is, that it be something that <hi>is hard or difficult;</hi> which difficulty hath an eye to something with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out us, as the help or means necessarily concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent to the attainment thereof; since no man is said properly to wait for that thing, which is absolutely in his own power, how and when he will to bestow upon himself. And this difficulty exercises and provokes <hi>courage, unto sedulity and perseverance,</hi> and puts metal into <hi>hope;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as that which is apprehended to come easily, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly and of course, makes the wil languish into a lazie presumption. Fiftly, S. <hi>Augustine</hi> adds <note place="margin">Aug. Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chir. cap. 8.</note> one more; and that is, that hope is of such good things, as <hi>concern our selves, only or chiefly,</hi> and so differs from <hi>faith,</hi> which is of greater latitude, and extends to any <hi>Truth</hi> at large; and when hope takes in the good that concerns other men, it is by the conjunction of <hi>charity,</hi> which is rare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly separated from the other two, in any of their actings. Now because some things that nearly and highly concern us, appear and are not only difficult, but impossible to nature, which yet are possible to grace; impossible to men, but yet <hi>possible unto God;</hi> therefore a Christians faith <note place="margin">Mat. 19. 26</note> and so his hope (which vertues many times in <hi>Scripture</hi> exchange both names and duties) is of a strain higher then his reason; as <hi>to know that
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:120110:6"/> which passeth knowledge,</hi> Eph. 3. so to <hi>believe in</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 3. 19.</note>
               <hi>hope, above or against hope,</hi> Rom. 4. as in the case <note place="margin">Rom. 4. 18</note> of <hi>Abraham</hi> to believe and expect, that strange and (only because God's not incredible) promise, of having a childe, <hi>when his own body and Sarahs womb were now as it were dead;</hi> that is <hi>barren;</hi> and in the <hi>date</hi> and strength of nature, past chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren: Such is the hope of the Resurrection from the dead, <hi>a hope above hope,</hi> as in another sense, <hi>out of the stones,</hi> so in this, <hi>out of the dust, to raise children unto Abraham,</hi> and so to all his children, <note place="margin">Mat. 3. 9.</note> who was called <hi>the father of the faithful</hi> Now in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed this hope here mentioned, is not either that <hi>natural passion of hope,</hi> nor yet that <hi>theological vertue of hope,</hi> singly or properly (for, to speak accurately, hope in that sense, is in this life only, in the chief exercise of it) for in heaven, <hi>faith</hi> shall be turned into <hi>vision,</hi> and <hi>love</hi> into <hi>union;</hi> and then <hi>hope</hi> shall be turned into <hi>fruition,</hi> and <hi>hope that is seen, is not hope: for what a man seeth</hi> (or enjoyeth) <hi>why doth he yet hope for it? Rom.</hi> 8. But it is the object of hope or the thing <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 24</note> hoped for, that is here intended; <hi>the hope which is laid up for us in heaven,</hi> as S. <hi>Paul</hi> sayes, <hi>Col.</hi> 1. <note place="margin">Col. 1. 5.</note> which faith, <hi>the substance of the things hoped for, and the evidence of things not seen;</hi> so antidates <note place="margin">Heb. 11. 1.</note> for the time, and represents unto us in the manner of a <hi>divine prospective glasse;</hi> that, that which is a far off in the place, and time of the accomplish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is very near in the assurance and appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hension; yea rather, the comprehension of it. Yet neverthelesse it is in relation unto, and under the excercise of this passion, and of this vertue, of hope here, waiting for it, and rejoycing in it, as in a just and indubitate, as in a certain and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defeizable,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:120110:6"/> right, title and interest in reversion, to great things. This is the Christians hope. This is that we are <hi>chosen unto, even the hope of eternal life, which God, that cannot lie, promised before the world began,</hi> Tit. 1. This is that we are <note place="margin">Tit. 1. 2.</note>
               <hi>begotten unto, by the resurrection of Jesus Christ,</hi> (who hath purchased it by his death, compleated and settled it, by his resurrection) <hi>even to a lively hope,</hi> 1 Pet. 1. This is that <hi>we are called unto, in one hope of our calling,</hi> Eph. 4. this being [sure <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1. 3. Eph. 4. 4.</note> enough] <hi>the price of the high calling of God in Christ Jesus,</hi> Phil. 3. unto this we are <hi>sanctified,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 3. 14.</note>
               <hi>that we might have good hope, through grace,</hi> 2 Thes. 2. both as <hi>grace</hi> refers to the <hi>fountain,</hi> whence it is graciously given; and as it refers to <note place="margin">2 Thes. 2. 16.</note> the <hi>water,</hi> which is grace it self, given, and given, as a sure pledge, that God will own both it and us; given us as a <hi>well of water within us, spring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up into everlasting life,</hi> John 4. for grace is <note place="margin">John. 4. 14</note> nothing lesse, then glory inchoated, and glory nothing more, then grace consummate, when we shall enjoy that <hi>blessed hope</hi> (which now with wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering eyes and longing hearts, we wait for) <hi>even the glorious appearing of the great God and our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tit. 2. 13.</note>
               <hi>Jesus Christ.</hi> This is that blessed hope, that lively hope, as it is called, &amp; wel may be so, that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends &amp; relies upon such lively and such precious merits and promises: <hi>exceeding great and pretious promises,</hi> 2 Pet. 1. <hi>Great</hi> in the greatnesse of the <note place="margin">2 Pet. 1. 4.</note> things promised; great both in their value, and in their durablenesse, spiritual and eternal things; and <hi>great</hi> in the greatnesse of the promise, who is the great <hi>God</hi> himself, wise and good, potent and constant; divine attributes abundantly enough to create confidence, and to corroborate
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:120110:7"/> hope into an humble assurance. <hi>Faithful is he that hath promised, who also will do it,</hi> 1 Thes. 5. <note place="margin">1 Thes. 5. 23.</note> and <hi>I know whom I have trusted, and that he is able to keep that which I have committed to him,</hi> 2 Tim. 1. This is the <hi>Saints helmet: take for a</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 1. 12. 1 Thes. 5. 8. 1 Pet. 1. 5. Heb. 6. 19.</note>
               <hi>helmet the hope of salvation,</hi> 1 Thes. 5. A <hi>helmet</hi> that cannot be battered nor beaten off, because it is made and kept on by a sure hand. This is the <hi>anker of the soul,</hi> Heb. 6. 19. <hi>which hope we have as an anker of the soul, both sure and stedfast, and which entreth into that within the veil:</hi> An <hi>anker</hi> forged by the finger of <hi>God</hi> himself, which <note place="margin">Lu. 11. 20 Mat. 12, 28.</note> is his <hi>Spirit,</hi> and fixed in heaven, in the <hi>truth of God it self,</hi> and so fastned to a cable that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be cut or broke, the promise of God let down unto us in the Scripture; yea, let down into us by the holy Ghost. It was the folly of <hi>Tyrus</hi> (as it is described at large <hi>Ezek.</hi> 27.) that <note place="margin">Ezek. 27.</note> having made provision of all necessaries for a voyage to Sea, both as to the hull and tacklings, and marriners, there is no mention of <hi>ankers</hi> in all the inventory: and such is the misery and madnesse of all such, as being to sail on the <hi>sea of this world,</hi> where they must needs expect storms and billows, are yet without <hi>the anker of hope;</hi> such are all unregenerate men, that are <hi>without Christ, having no hope,</hi> Eph. 2. a sad thing, to be <note place="margin">Eph. 2. 12.</note> without a <hi>helmet in a day of battel,</hi> especially where they go to it with down-right blows: a sad thing to be <hi>at sea in a storm, without an anker,</hi> or to have an anker that will start and lose its hold and come home, and so the ship be driven to and again, at the mercy of the windes. Such was his condition, that lay languishing on his death<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, saying, <hi>doubting I have lived, and doubting
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:120110:7"/> I die,</hi> I <hi>know not whither</hi> I <hi>go, even farewell friends. Job</hi> sayes of the hypocrites hope, that <hi>it shall perish, and shall be cut off, and his trust</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 8. 13, 14.</note>
               <hi>shall be as a spiders web</hi> Job 8. A spiders web, that is curiously wrought, but soon swept down, of no strength, of no stead, such is the hope, rather the presumption, of the <hi>hypocrite,</hi> and such it will prove to them that fix their preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded hopes on Gods unconditioned mercy, or on naturall abilities, or on morall preparations, or on their own merits, or on works of superero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, the Churches abundancie, or on any thing, but that on which the Christians hope is lodged and fixed, and that is <hi>on Christ,</hi> which hastens us, to the second particular.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Christians have their hope in Christ.</hi> Now, <hi>O</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>2</label>
               <hi>Lord, what is my hope? truely my hope is even in thee,</hi> saith holy <hi>David,</hi> Psal. 39. even in <hi>our Lord</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 39. 7.</note>
               <hi>Jesus Christ, who is our hope,</hi> saith S. <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 Tim. 1. <note place="margin">1 Tim. 1. 1</note> from him we derive all our right and interest to grace and glory, <hi>we in Christ, and Christ in us,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 1. 27.</note>
               <hi>the hope of glory,</hi> Col. 1. Christ is the foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a Christians hope: In this <hi>our elder Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 27.</note>
               <hi>garment,</hi> we receive the blessing, not by supplantation, but by consent, and by a graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous compact, for <hi>(a filio filiatio nostra)</hi> from this <hi>Son of God,</hi> we come into <hi>son-ship</hi> with the <note place="margin">Gal. 3. 27.</note> Father, and into the priviledges of it; <hi>children, and if children, heirs; heirs, and coheirs with Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 17.</note>
               <hi>Christ,</hi> Rom. 8. This is the generall claim of Christians, their plea, their tenure; we hold all, in Capite, from him; <hi>All things are yours, and</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 3. 22</note>
               <hi>you are Christs,</hi> 1 Cor. 3. and <hi>all the promises of God,</hi> (the charter of our hopes) <hi>are in him, yea, and in him, Amen,</hi> 2 Cor. 1. Out of <hi>Christ,</hi> we <note place="margin">2 Cor. 1. 20</note>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:120110:8"/> must needs be out of all <hi>hope</hi> of respect or union with <hi>God,</hi> whom sin hath set at such an infinite distance from him, farre below the basenesse of our mortall condition: for what is <hi>the daughter of the thistle,</hi> till she be <hi>married</hi> to the <hi>son of the Cedar?</hi> It is the union, the marriage of our flesh, with the <hi>Son of God,</hi> by his incarnation, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nobles our blood, and gives us a title of the <hi>kings daughter</hi> (not by birth, as <hi>Thamar,</hi> the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <note place="margin">Psal. 45. 13</note> of King <hi>David,</hi> but as <hi>Esther,</hi> a poor bond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maid, <note place="margin">Esther.</note> but freely beloved, chosen by, and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to King <hi>Ahasuerus)</hi> so are we, <hi>as a chaste virgin, espoused unto one husband, even to Christ,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 11. 2</note> by a particular right, and in a double sence, <hi>made partakers of the divine nature,</hi> 2 Pet. 1. <note place="margin">2 Pet. 1. 4.</note> What are the <hi>children of darknesse,</hi> untill they are <hi>engrafted into the stock of light?</hi> What is the <hi>issue</hi> of sinfull corruption, untill they bee <hi>adopted</hi> into the family of grace and hope, which is in <hi>Christ Jesus.</hi> It is his assuming our nature <note place="margin">Heb. 2. 16.</note> that advances us even above the Angels: it is his righteousnesse, his active and passive obedience, <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 33.</note> that makes us <hi>hold weight, in the ballance of the sanctuary:</hi> it is his intercession, that ingratiates our persons, and our petitions, and, <hi>as incense,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 4.</note>
               <hi>perfumes our prayers offered up on his golden al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, and out of his fulnesse, we all receive, even</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 1. 16</note>
               <hi>grace for grace,</hi> John 1.</p>
            <p>A perfect Embleme of our Blessed Saviour, and our interest in him, we have in that <hi>ladder Jacob saw in his dream,</hi> Gen. 28. <hi>The foot there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 28. 12</note>
               <hi>stood upon earth,</hi> in reference to his <hi>humanity,</hi> and the <hi>top of it reached to heaven,</hi> in order to his <hi>Divinity:</hi> His <hi>incarnation, circumcision, temptation, holy life, his passion, crucifixion, bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:120110:8"/> resurrection, ascension, session at Gods right hand, his intercession, and mission of the Holy Ghost,</hi> are the severall <hi>rounds of this ladder.</hi> And as the <hi>Angels ascended and descended,</hi> by and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this <hi>ladder,</hi> so all our <hi>adresses, and all our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turus, to and again,</hi> are made by, and upon <hi>Him:</hi> our prayers, and praises, and alms-deeds, and all our hopes and wishes, go up this <hi>ladder:</hi> all his graces, and his promises, and his comforts, all come down this <hi>ladder;</hi> even all our hope what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever is in <hi>Christ,</hi> which is (in part) in this life, and leads us to the third particular.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Christians have hope in Christ, even in this life.</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>3</label>
               <hi>Godlinesse</hi> (as S. <hi>Paul</hi> sayes) <hi>hath the promise of this life:</hi> It hath the promise of this life, and <note place="margin">1 Tim. 4. 8.</note> in this life. First, of <hi>this life,</hi> and the <hi>things of this life,</hi> as to the <hi>spiritual right,</hi> and secondly, as to the <hi>sanctified and comfortable use</hi> of them, and thirdly, as they are <hi>evidences of Gods inward love,</hi> and fourthly, <hi>pledges of better things</hi> to come. Wicked men have them not so (though their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall or civill right to them, may be unquestio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, <hi>as their portion in this life:)</hi> but (which is much more) even in this life, they have the <note place="margin">Psal. 17. 14</note> promises of a better, and so a title to it <hi>(jus ad rem)</hi> even here, and now, a right to heaven, and to eternity. <hi>All things are yours, [saith the Apostle] whether Paul or Apollo, or Cephas,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 3. 21, 22.</note>
               <hi>or the world, or life, or death, or things present, or things to come, all are yours,</hi> 1 Cor. 3. And <hi>Beloved now are we the sons of God,</hi> saith S. <hi>John,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Joh. 3. 2.</note> 1 John 3. <hi>Sons under age,</hi> indeed, and not yet come to be <hi>(adulti)</hi> of full yeers, to be <hi>heirs</hi> in possession, yet <hi>sons and heirs</hi> we are, in right of reversion, and have received that which is the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:120110:9"/>
               <hi>earnest of our inheritance,</hi> Ephes. 1. Now the <hi>earnest</hi> is not onely a <hi>pledge,</hi> but <hi>a part of the bargain:</hi> And doubtlesse God will not forfeit, cannot lose his earnest, as S. <hi>Chrysostom</hi> sweetly; <note place="margin">Chrys. in 2. Cor. 1. hom. 3.</note> we have it upon his word, and under his seal, and he hath given earnest of it, and that no lesse then his own eternall and unchangeable <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, being sealed with that holy Spirit of promise,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ephes. 1. 13. 14.</note>
               <hi>which is the earnest of our inheritance, untill the redemption of the purchased possession, unto the praise of his glory:</hi> This is, by the same Apostle, called <hi>the first fruits of the spirit,</hi> Rom. 8. and the <hi>first fruits</hi> sanctifie all the <hi>harvest,</hi> or <hi>vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 23</note> and intitle us comfortably to the whole <hi>crop.</hi> These are as the fair <hi>cluster of grapes,</hi> brought down out of the land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> by them that went to make a search of it, and brought down for an <hi>Essay,</hi> to shew what fruit the vines of <hi>Canaan</hi> bore, <hi>Num.</hi> 13. This is that <note place="margin">Num. 13. 23.</note> which is given us for a <hi>taste,</hi> to <hi>whet our appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tites,</hi> and to <hi>stay</hi> our stomacks, as the Church prayes passionately in the <hi>Canticles, Stay me with</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2. 3.</note>
               <hi>flagons, and comfort me with apples, for I am sick of love.</hi> These are the <hi>flagons,</hi> to <hi>stay</hi> us a while, <note place="margin">Cant. 2. 5.</note> and to refresh us, till we come into the <hi>wine-seller;</hi> these are the <hi>apples</hi> to comfort us, till we come into the <hi>orchard, unto the tree of life.</hi> These are as the <hi>full sacks,</hi> and as the <hi>waggons, Joseph</hi> sent down to his <hi>father Jacob,</hi> but as a <note place="margin">Gen. 45.</note> token of what shall be. But this is not all, nor one half, <hi>for Christians have not their hopes in Christ, in this life onely,</hi> which is the fourth par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Christians have not their hope in Christ, in</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>4</label>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 4. 8</note>
               <hi>this life onely, Godlinesse hath the promise of this
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:120110:9"/> life, and that which is to come:</hi> And <hi>now we are the sons of God, but it doth not yet appear, what</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Joh. 3. 2.</note>
               <hi>we shall be: but we know when Christ shall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, we shall be like him,</hi> or, <hi>we shall see him, as he is. Sons</hi> we are, and <hi>heirs,</hi> though <hi>(nondum apparet)</hi> not yet <hi>heirs apparent:</hi> but we know, we shall be like him; we know, by the assurance of <hi>hope,</hi> and of <hi>adherence;</hi> we know, by the <hi>assurance of his promise, and of his Spirit,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though we do not see him yet, by the <hi>evidence of vision, of fruition,</hi> yet we shall <hi>see</hi> him, in his <note place="margin">Joh. 17. 21, 22.</note> glory, as he is, and be, as he is; <hi>we shall be like him,</hi> as like as like may be, as far as our <hi>capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city will reach,</hi> and that <hi>humble distance</hi> will admit us, which our <hi>scantling of grace</hi> has pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared us for; we shall be <hi>like him,</hi> in the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipation of his glorious perfections, and <hi>beati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes:</hi> we have here, but <hi>jus ad rem,</hi> there we shall have <hi>jus in re,</hi> here an <hi>expectation,</hi> there a <hi>fruition,</hi> here a <hi>reversion,</hi> there a <hi>possession:</hi> Here we stand, as <hi>Moses</hi> on a hill, and take a view of <hi>Canaan</hi> at a distance, but then and there, as <hi>Caleb</hi> and <hi>Joshua,</hi> we shall enter and enjoy that <note place="margin">Deut. 34. 1, 4.</note> good land which floweth with milk and honey, whereof <hi>Canaan</hi> was but a type: Here with <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> we have <hi>news of Joseph,</hi> and see the <hi>wag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 45.</note> that is, partake of the promises and the glad-tidings that are sent us, but then we shall go up and <hi>see Joseph, our Brother,</hi> that will freely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, all the injuries we have done him, and high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prefer us, I say not, in <hi>Egypt,</hi> but in <hi>Heaven,</hi> where he is <hi>Governour</hi> in Chief, <hi>In whose pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 16.</note>
               <hi>is fulnesse of joy, and at his right hand are pleasures for evermore. I beleeve that my Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 19.</note>
               <hi>liveth, and that</hi> I <hi>shall see him with these
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:120110:10"/> eyes. This was Jobs Creed. O how great is thy goodnesse which thou hast laid up for them that fear thee? This was Dauids meditation. We</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 31. 19</note>
               <hi>know when this earthly tabernacle shall be dissol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5. 1.</note>
               <hi>we have a building of God, a house not made with hands eternall in the heavens:</hi> This is the Saints generall assurance, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. and S. <hi>Paul</hi> for his own particular, I <hi>have fought a good fight, I have finished my course,</hi> I <hi>have kept the faith, from henceforth there is laid up for me, a crown of</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 4. 8.</note>
               <hi>righteousnesse, which the Lord, the righteous Judge, shall give me at that day,</hi> 2 Tim. 4. <hi>Henceforth,</hi> not <hi>here,</hi> not <hi>now,</hi> there is <hi>laid up,</hi> in the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable <hi>decree of God,</hi> in the <hi>infallible pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise of God,</hi> in the <hi>unconquerable hands and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God,</hi> there is <hi>laid up, a crown of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnesse,</hi> a crown not of <hi>bayes,</hi> or of <hi>laurell,</hi> for that may <hi>wither,</hi> not of <hi>silver or of gold,</hi> for <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1. 4.</note> that may <hi>canker;</hi> not a crown of <hi>gold,</hi> but of <hi>glory,</hi> not a <hi>crown of gold, set with diamonds,</hi> but a <hi>crown of glory, set with stars,</hi> or with some things richer then stars, <hi>grace, and peace, and immortality:</hi> and this the <hi>righteous Judge</hi> will do, <hi>righteous,</hi> not to us, in the justnesse of our merit, <hi>(Lord enter not into judgement with thy servants,</hi> said one of the best of his servants) <note place="margin">Psal. 14.</note>
               <hi>but righteous to himselfe,</hi> to his own <hi>word,</hi> who hath graciously promised it, and so made him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self <note place="margin">Aug.</note> both a <hi>donour, and a debtour;</hi> and <hi>righteous to his Son,</hi> who hath dearly earned, and justly <hi>won</hi> this crown, that we might <hi>wear it,</hi> and hath prepared it for our heads. There are three things, which when I consider sadly, my heart faints and dies within me; they are, the <hi>indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of my person,</hi> the <hi>imperfection of my best
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:120110:10"/> works,</hi> and <hi>that huge disproportion, that is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt me, a poor-mortall-sinfull creature, and a glorious everlasting crown,</hi> promised, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore expected, from God. But there are three things to set against them, able to support me <note place="margin">Bern. de fragmen. 7. miserie. ser. 3.</note> at the lowest; that is, first <hi>the free love of my heavenly Father,</hi> that hath <hi>adopted me;</hi> secondly the <hi>faithfulnesse of his word,</hi> that hath <hi>promised me;</hi> and thirdly <hi>the omnipotencie of his power to performe what he hath promised;</hi> I will add a fourth, it is, the <hi>perfect and infinite merit of my Saviour, who hath redeemed me, and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chased this glory for me;</hi> and though I am utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly unworthy, yet is he <hi>worthy,</hi> both as to that I hope for in this life, and not in this life onely. It is said of <hi>Alexander the Great</hi> (great in every mans mouth) that as he conquered severall Towns and Countries, he bestowed them royally on his followers, and when he was asked, what he would reserve for himself, he answered, <hi>Hope;</hi> and yet at last when he had conquered all the <hi>World,</hi> (as the estimate of the world then went) he is said, to have sate down, and <hi>to have wept, that there were no more Worlds to conquer:</hi> and weep he might, poor man, after all his victories, and mourn, <hi>as a man without hope,</hi> that was ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant <note place="margin">1 Thes. 4. 13.</note> of another world, a world to come, of another kingdom, not yet conquered, not yet heard of, <hi>the kingdom of heaven,</hi> which is said <hi>to suffer violence, and the violent to take it by</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 11. 12</note>
               <hi>force.</hi> This, this is the misery of the <hi>men of this</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psa. 17. 14.</note>
               <hi>world, that they have their portion in this life onely;</hi> who build their hope or trust on riches, or on honour, or on strength, or on Princes, or on any thing under the Sun, for <hi>they die and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:120110:11"/> and their hopes, and their thoughts, perish with them.</hi> But <hi>the righteous hath hope in his</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 14. 32.</note>
               <hi>death;</hi> and it goes with him to his grave, and it leaves him not there, as his dearest-friends do, for his hope is not at an end, untill he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives <hi>the end of his hope, which is the salvation of his soul;</hi> and if it were not so, but that the hope and the happinesse of a Christian determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with this present life, if he had his hope in this life onely, he were of all men most miserable, which is our fifth particular.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If Christians had their hope in Christ in this</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>5</label>
               <hi>life onely, they were then of all men most miserable.</hi> For what is a mans <hi>life</hi> at the best, but a <hi>warfare upon earth?</hi> and what is this <hi>earth</hi> at best, but a <hi>thorow-fare?</hi> and what are we else, <hi>but stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 39. 12</note>
               <hi>and pilgrims as all our fathers were?</hi> Now what do strangers finde in their travail home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, but cold <hi>windes</hi> in their face, <hi>foul wayes, hard lodgings</hi> in their <hi>Inne,</hi> and sharp <hi>reckonings, Ex vita exeo, tanquam ex hospitio,</hi> said a wise <note place="margin">Seneca.</note> Heathen, I go out of the <hi>World</hi> as out of an <hi>Inne.</hi> This is common to men; but Christians, it may be hoped, finde better entertainment in the world: nay, but much worse, <hi>For we are</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 4. 9,</note>
               <hi>made</hi> (saith S. <hi>Paul)</hi> or <hi>set out, as a spectacle, as a gazing stock, to the world, to Angels and to men: Even to this present hour, we hunger and</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/>
               <hi>thirst, and are naked, and are buffetted, and</hi> (as vagrants) <hi>have no certain dwelling place; and labour, working with our hands, reviled, persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/>
               <hi>and defamed; yea, worse yet, we are made as the filth of the world, and as the off-scouring of all things,</hi> as the <hi>faeces,</hi> or <hi>dregs,</hi> or <hi>refuse,</hi> or something perhaps more foul then modesty
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:120110:11"/> would have named. This is the estimation, this the entertainment that the followers of <hi>Jesus,</hi> yea the <hi>prime</hi> of them, the <hi>Apostles</hi> themselves, had in this life. Read the history of S. <hi>Pauls</hi> usage, under his own hand, 2 <hi>Cor. 4. We are</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 4. 8.</note>
               <hi>troubled on every side (yet not distressed) we are perplexed [but not in despair] persecuted [but</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/>
               <hi>not forsaken,] cast down [but not destroyed,] alwayes bearing about in the body, the dying of our</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/>
               <hi>Lord Jesus, and we which live are alwayes deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered over unto death, for Jesus sake:</hi> And again, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> Chap. 11. <hi>In labours abundant: in stripes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chap. 11. 23.</note>
               <hi>measure, in prisons frequent: in deaths oft: of the Jews five times I received fourty stripes</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="24"/>
               <hi>save one: thrice was I beaten with rods: once was I stoned: thrice I suffered shipwrack: in journey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="25"/>
               <hi>often, in perils of waters, in perils of robbers, in perils by mine own countreymen, in perils by</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="26"/>
               <hi>the heathen, in perils in the city, in perils in the wildernesse, in perils in the sea, in perils among false brethren: in wearinesse, and painfulnesse,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="27"/>
               <hi>in watchings often, in hunger and thirst, in fast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings often, in cold and nakedness.</hi> I see it pities you, it wearies you to hear it, oh how would it weary you to bear it? yet such was the usage of the best Christians, in this life. Take an extract of the usage of all the primitive Saints, almost all the world over. <hi>Heb. 11. Some were tortured,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 11. 35.</note>
               <hi>others had triall of cruel mockings and scourg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, yea moreover of bonds and imprisonment, they were stoned, they were sawen asunder, were</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="36"/>
               <hi>tempted, were slain with the sword, they wandred</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="37"/>
               <hi>about in sheep-skins, and goats-skins, being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitute, afflicted, tormented, they wandred in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serts,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="38"/>
               <hi>and in mountains, and in dens, and caves
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:120110:12"/> of the earth, of whom the world was not worthy,</hi> and yet the world counted them not worthy of the least civilities, yea rather worthy of the most exquisite cruelties. Read the bloody <hi>Records</hi> of the ten persecutions; read the <hi>Ecclesiasticall Histories</hi> of all times, first or last, and you must needs conclude; <hi>If Christians had their hope in Christ in this life only, they weremore miserable then any men:</hi> for other men are of other mindes, and so of other wayes then <hi>Christians</hi> are: as for <hi>Epicures,</hi> they can, upon their own <hi>principles,</hi> indulge and pamper their <hi>genius,</hi> and let them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves loose and at large, to all sensuall pleasures, as if the earth were given them, <hi>as the sea to the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 104. 26.</note>
               <hi>Leviathan, to take their pastime in:</hi> Jollitie and dalliance is the highest good, they aim at, and therefore they <hi>rant</hi> it one to another, as those revelling Romans did, saying, <hi>(Dum vivimus vivamus) Let us eat and drink for to morrow we</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 13.</note>
               <hi>shall die;</hi> and when we are gone, all is gone with us. For <hi>we are born</hi> (say they) <hi>at all ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventures,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Wisd. 2. 2.</note>
               <hi>and we shall be hereafter, as if we never had been, for the breath in our nostrils is as smoak, and a little spark in the moving of our heart, which being extinguished, our bodies shall be turned into</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
               <hi>ashes, and our spirits shall vanish, as the soft air. For our time is a very shadow that passeth away,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/>
               <hi>and after our end, there is no returning, for it is fast sealed, so that no man cometh again. Come on therefore, let us enjoy the good things that are</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/>
               <hi>present, and let us speedily use the creatures, like as in youth. Let us fill our selves with costly</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/>
               <hi>wines and ointments; and let no flower of the spring passe by us. Let us crown our selves with rose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buds,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/>
               <hi>before they be withered, let none of us go
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:120110:12"/> without his share of our voluptuousnesse: let us</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/>
               <hi>leave tokens of our jollity in every place, for this <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> is our portion, and this our lot.</hi> Alas, this is their <hi>portion</hi> indeed, all they hope for: a <hi>messe of pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage,</hi> goes for profane <hi>Esau's blessing; Musick and a fatted calf, the prodigalls of the world,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 10</note> for their <hi>childs part,</hi> as that wild <hi>Atheist</hi> said, <hi>he would not quit his part in Paris, for his part in Paradise.</hi> Again, ungodly men are <hi>men of this world,</hi> and therefore this <hi>world owns</hi> and <note place="margin">Joh. 15. 19</note> loves them; and <hi>Satan</hi> the <hi>God of this world</hi> has no quarrell at them: they are <hi>Deer in his own Park,</hi> and <hi>tame Fowls in his own Yard,</hi> and at his command, and <hi>he</hi> (as <hi>Holofernes</hi> said) <hi>will</hi>
               <note place="margin">Judeth 11. 1.</note>
               <hi>never hurt any, that will serve Nebuchadonosor the king of all the earth:</hi> his <hi>deadly feud</hi> is against the servants of the <hi>King of heaven, Iob,</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> and <hi>Peter,</hi> and such as they shall feel his sting, if God restrain him not: as for others, whom Satan, <hi>the God of this world hath blinded,</hi> who <note place="margin">2 Cor. 4. 4.</note> are <hi>led captive by him at his will,</hi> they need not fear at present, whiles the <hi>strong man armed</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim, 2. 26.</note>
               <hi>keeps the house, all is quiet there.</hi> So long as <hi>Israel</hi> will do their <hi>tasks,</hi> and <hi>couch</hi> under <note place="margin">Luk. 11. 21</note> their <hi>bondage, Pharaoh</hi> sits still, but if once they turn their backs upon <hi>Egypt,</hi> he will soon pursue them, with all his might. 3. Yea, God himself is pleased a while to <hi>wink at his</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 17. 30</note>
               <hi>enemies,</hi> and to <hi>hold his peace,</hi> and to say within himself, <hi>Let them alone, why should</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psa. 50. 21.</note>
               <hi>they bee smitten any more?</hi> hee <hi>prunes</hi> not <note place="margin">Isai. 1. 5. James 5.</note>
               <hi>wilde vines,</hi> but lets them runne, reclaims not <hi>untamed heifers,</hi> but suffers them in his <hi>green pastures,</hi> to bee <hi>fatted to the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 73. 5.</note>
               <hi>slaughter. So that they are not in trouble as
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:120110:13"/> others, neither are they plagued as other men,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/>
               <hi>Therefore pride compasseth them about as a chain, and violence covereth them as a garment; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/>
               <hi>their eyes stick out with fatnesse, and they have more then their hearts can wish. Behold, these are</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/>
               <hi>the ungodly, who prosper in the world and encrease in riches. When all the day long I have been pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gued,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/>
               <hi>and chastened every morning.</hi> This trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled <hi>David,</hi> till he had recovered himself, by <hi>go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="17"/>
               <hi>into the sanctuary and by considering their end</hi> (that this is their share and their portion, a poor, short and sensual happinesse) <hi>and suddenly they</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="18"/>
               <hi>are cast down into destruction.</hi> Last of all, other men can <hi>dispense</hi> with their <hi>consciences,</hi> (by a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle mistake) <hi>serving the time instead of serving the Lord,</hi> they can keep a <hi>temper, comply, and serve</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 12. 11 <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> pro <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <hi>turns,</hi> and (in an evil sense) <hi>become all things to all men, to gain something, though they lose</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, in the end, by it: By this means they provoke no enemies (as to their <hi>religion</hi> at least) or indanger themselves, <hi>as Daniel, and the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 6. 10. Acts 4.</note>
               <hi>did,</hi> so they may sleep in a whole skin, and preserve their own <hi>interest</hi> with the world, they dare <hi>trust God with their souls,</hi> and for mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of lawful or unlawful, <hi>Gallio careth for none of these things.</hi> These <hi>censure and be fool other</hi> men, that betray themselves into sufferings, as too <hi>nice and tender,</hi> as too <hi>precise and scrupulous,</hi> accounting <hi>carnal pollicy,</hi> to be the only <hi>piety,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 6. 5</note> and <hi>gain to be godlinesse;</hi> by a <hi>fallacy of dividing</hi> what <hi>Christ</hi> hath <hi>joyned; the serpents wisdom,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 10. 16</note>
               <hi>from the doves innocency.</hi> But the Saints cannot do so, cannot give or take to themselves liberty, <hi>to become the servants of men, by a sinful compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 7. 23</note> or <hi>to warp to the sunny side,</hi> when their
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:120110:13"/> duty and conscience strongly inclines them ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way: <hi>God corrects every son that he receiveth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 12. 6.</note>
               <hi>and whom he loves he chastiseth,</hi> lest they should wax wanton and unworthy of the sincere disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline of such a father. Satan is their <hi>sworn ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 12. 10</note> who are <hi>Gods friends, the accuser of the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,</hi> and <hi>let loose</hi> upon them some times, for their trial, exercise and glory; yea, and they in assured hope of a better life, are content to accept of <hi>Christs tearms</hi> in this, (being no worse then he under-went himself for us, and before us) that is, <hi>through many tribulations to enter into the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 14. 22</note>
               <hi>kingdom of God:</hi> for this is the general rule <hi>(via regia)</hi> the great <hi>road of Christendom; All they</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3. 12.</note>
               <hi>that wil live godly in Christ must suffer persecution</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>:) they that <hi>will,</hi> that are <hi>resolved</hi> upon it, what ere it cost them; resolved to <hi>walk urightly</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) to walk <hi>strictly</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) they shall, they must prepare, to suffer for it; We are not called to be Christs Disciples upon any other conditions, then to <hi>take up his crosse and</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 16.</note>
               <hi>follow him;</hi> nor promised to reign with him, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse we also suffer with him. Did <hi>Christ our ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 2. 12</note>
               <hi>drink of any other cup,</hi> and must not we <hi>pledge</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 20. 23 Mat. 10. 25</note>
               <hi>him in the same cup, though it be gall and vinegar? it is enough that the disciple be as the master.</hi> They that go about to pull the <hi>crosse</hi> out of the <hi>Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans arms,</hi> spoyl the whole <hi>coat,</hi> if I have any skill, in the <hi>herauldry of heaven:</hi> they prevent the glory of martyrdom, and <hi>deflowre</hi> the Saints of their <hi>prime</hi> renown, <hi>whose robes were died white</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 7. 14.</note>
               <hi>in bloud,</hi> double died <hi>in bloud,</hi> their <hi>Saviours</hi> and their <hi>own:</hi> whose glory shines most bright in their sufferings; as <hi>silver vessels (vessels of</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 2. 21.</note>
               <hi>honour) scoured</hi> with scorn and cruelties, by the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:120110:14"/>
               <hi>Devils scullions</hi> upon earth: <hi>here is the faith and patience of the Saints;</hi> and <hi>these are they that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 13. 10. 14. 4.</note>
               <hi>the Lamb whithersoever he goeth.</hi> Those then that misapply the doctrine of <hi>Christian pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> and <hi>self-preservation,</hi> to save their skins, and to avoid their sufferings <hi>for righteousnesse sake</hi> and a good conscience, seem to me to attempt to pluck out the <hi>thorns out of Christs crown,</hi> which is made up of them, &amp; so mar it in the mending, and prevent the <hi>crown of martyrdom.</hi> These men surely dream of a temporal <hi>kingdom of Christ,</hi> as some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times <note place="margin">Acts 1. 6.</note> the <hi>Apostle</hi> did, and could hardly be <hi>beaten out of that haunt,</hi> or to have fained to themselves a smoother, easier, way to heaven, then that the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles and confessors of Christ, &amp; Christ himself,</hi> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>went,</hi> or <hi>chalked out</hi> for us to go by. No, no, this life is not the place for Saints to receive their <note place="margin">1 Cor. 9. 24 2 Tim. 4. 8. Mat. 20. 1.</note> hopes in: this is their <hi>race,</hi> to <hi>run in,</hi> their <hi>field to fight in,</hi> their <hi>vineyard to work in;</hi> a <hi>glassie sea,</hi> a <hi>fiery furnace,</hi> a <hi>valley of tears;</hi> and <hi>had they their hopes in this life only, they were of all</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 16.</note>
               <hi>men most miserable.</hi> Then were the <hi>rich-man,</hi> with the <hi>purple</hi> and <hi>fine linen,</hi> and his <hi>dainty fare,</hi> to be adjudged more happy then poor <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus,</hi> that lay at his door, on whom the <hi>dogs</hi> took more pitty then their <hi>master</hi> did: then should <hi>Herod</hi> have been accounted more happy, then <hi>John Baptist, Saul</hi> then <hi>David;</hi> when <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 20. 26.</note>
               <hi>was hunted by Saul like a partridge upon the mountains.</hi> Saul is the <hi>hawk,</hi> a proud <hi>bird of prey, man'd</hi> and <hi>dieted</hi> and <hi>carried on the fist,</hi> with her <hi>velvet hood,</hi> her <hi>silver varvels,</hi> her <hi>sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken jesses,</hi> her <hi>gingling bels,</hi> and attendants after her, which <hi>whistled</hi> off the fist upon her wings, lessens her self in the <hi>air,</hi> watching till the poor <hi>partridge</hi> be sprung to her pleasure. But <hi>David
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:120110:14"/> is as the partridge,</hi> safe no where, but in a sad <hi>dilemma</hi> for her life; if she <hi>rise</hi> she is in danger of the <hi>hawke,</hi> if she <hi>flick</hi> on the ground, she is in danger of the <hi>dog:</hi> but marke the end, when the hawke dies, she is stript of her ornaments, and cast out unto the <hi>dung-hil,</hi> as a <hi>carrion kite:</hi> but when the <hi>partridge</hi> is killed, she is carefully <hi>drest and served up in a dish for princes.</hi> This is the difference then, of such <hi>as fear God,</hi> and such <hi>as fear him not,</hi> of such as have <hi>hope, hope in Christ,</hi> in <hi>Christ in this life,</hi> but <hi>not in this life only;</hi> surely they cannot be of all men most <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serable;</hi> surely they cannot but be of all men <hi>most happy,</hi> which (as the rebounding of the text) is the last particular.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Christians having hope, and if in Christ, and</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>6</label>
               <hi>that in this life, and not in this life onely, are of all men most happy, and that they may be compleatly happy, may sure enough expect a resurrection of the body. Blessed are the dead that die in the Lord: hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth, even so saith the Spirit, for they rest from their labours and their works follow them,</hi> Rev. 14. <note place="margin">Rev. 14. 13</note> Their <hi>good works die</hi> not with them, they <hi>follow them,</hi> those that <hi>went before</hi> them in the <hi>perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance,</hi> follow them in their <hi>good fame</hi> among men. 2. In their <hi>good acceptance and reward</hi> with God; the works done in the <hi>body,</hi> shall be rewarded, and therefore <hi>the body</hi> it self must needs rise again; <hi>in which, and by which,</hi> they <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5. 10</note> were done, that <hi>reward</hi> may be <hi>done in kind.</hi> Can we reasonably imagine or believe, that <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God,</hi> who <hi>fashioned the body</hi> by his own <note place="margin">Gen. 2. 7.</note>
               <hi>hands, quickned</hi> it with his own <hi>breath, honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it with</hi> his own <hi>likenesse, fitted</hi> it to be the <hi>habitation of the soul,</hi> which in it first is <hi>capable of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:120110:15"/> grace,</hi> and in it only of the <hi>means of grace,</hi> the holy <hi>word</hi> and <hi>Sacraments,</hi> who <hi>allows</hi> it to be his <hi>chappel</hi> and <hi>chaplaine</hi> for <hi>prayers,</hi> his <hi>almo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner for bounties and good works,</hi> his <hi>votary and martyr,</hi> in <hi>watching, fasting, continency, endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring cold, nakednesse, shame, imprisonment, stripes,</hi> yea, and <hi>death it self</hi> for <hi>Gods cause,</hi> can we think that that <hi>body</hi> shall not rise again from the <hi>grave</hi> and have a <hi>share</hi> in glory? Can we believe, that <hi>body</hi> which <hi>Christ</hi> so ennobled, as to assume it <note place="margin">John 1. 14. 1 Cor. 6. 19</note> unto his <hi>diuine nature,</hi> which the <hi>holy Ghost</hi> so graced, as to make it his <hi>temple,</hi> and which Christ hath taken with him as <hi>our pledge,</hi> speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fically into <hi>heaven,</hi> when he <hi>ascended</hi> thither as <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="15"/>
               <hi>our head,</hi> that we may be well assured the <hi>head and members</hi> cannot be for ever separated, and shall not this <hi>body</hi> rise again from the dead? Can he that commanded us to love our <hi>neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour</hi> as our self (sayes <hi>Tertullian)</hi> forget that <hi>flesh</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tertul. de Resur. Car. cap. 9.</note> to which he was so near <hi>allied,</hi> so <hi>near neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> when <hi>he dwelt amongst us?</hi> No, no, but as the soul and body <hi>took sweet counsel together upon earth,</hi> fasted, prayed, <hi>and went to the house of God as friends,</hi> so they shall <hi>share</hi> together in fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitie, though <hi>divorced</hi> awhile by death, they shall be <hi>married again,</hi> and live and love toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to all <hi>eternity. Non possunt separari in mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede, caro &amp; anima, quas in operibus conjunxit. Absit, absit ut Deus manuum suarum operam, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genii sui curam, afflatus sui vaginam, molitionis suae reginam, liberalitatis suae haeredem, religionis suae sacerdotem, testimonii sui militem, Christi sui sororem in aeternum destituat interitum,</hi> saith the same father. Neither can the soul be compleat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly happy without the body, nor the body with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:120110:15"/> the soul; the <hi>soul</hi> takes possession first, but the <hi>body</hi> rests in hope, waiting the good time, when the <hi>trumpet shall blow, and the dead bodies shal rise incorruptible,</hi> 1 Cor. 15. 52. Such a day the saints may sure enough promise to themselves, knowing they serve a <hi>good master,</hi> and <hi>their works shal not be in vain in the Lord,</hi> verse 58. Not in <hi>vain,</hi> not <hi>of all men the most miserable,</hi> which negation of vanity or misery, may imply the contrary, in a strong and high elegancy. The day of a good mans death, is the last of his <hi>combates,</hi> and the first of his <hi>triumphs;</hi> the <hi>last enemy that shal be subdued</hi> (above ground) <hi>is death,</hi> and death it self is subdued for us, and <hi>the grave</hi> is only a <hi>dormitorie,</hi> a <hi>with-drawing chamber</hi> for a while: a good mans <hi>grave</hi> is his <hi>bed,</hi> where he <hi>rests from his labours,</hi> both from his sorrows and his sins. Why then should friends mourn, <hi>as men without hope,</hi> 1 Thes. 4. for them that died in a lively hope, <hi>candidates and expectants of that blessed hope,</hi> to be conpleated at <hi>the glorious appearing of Jesus Christ:</hi> yea, and in their better part, are gone out already to meet it, and to enjoy it? why should our griefs and out-cries, so much as <hi>call</hi> them or <hi>wish</hi> them back again, who are now in their <hi>haven,</hi> and at their <hi>rest?</hi> you <hi>bid them to their loss,</hi> to <hi>engage</hi> them to begin that <hi>warfare</hi> againe, which they have happily <hi>finished.</hi> This is no place intended for the <hi>felicitie or securitie</hi> of the <hi>Saints;</hi> here 1. the <hi>body</hi> is mortal, crazie and corruptible: 2. the <hi>soul</hi> clogg'd with infirmities, and corruptions. 3. The Church mixt of good and bad: 4. this is <hi>Satans walk,</hi> where he has leave and time to <hi>range and tempt.</hi> 5. This was never intended for our <hi>home,</hi> our <hi>fathers house;</hi> here are none of the <hi>Patriarchs, Prophets, Apostles, Martyrs, nor Jesus Christ himself,</hi> without whom <hi>heaven</hi> it self could not be a <hi>happy place.</hi> No, no, <hi>migremus hinc</hi> (as the voice said at <hi>Jerusalem</hi> awhile before the <hi>fatal</hi> ruines of it) <hi>let us away hence, let us away hence. Volemus ad coelum, Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stiani,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:120110:16"/> volemus ad coelum</hi> (as holy <hi>Monica</hi> in a devout <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tasie)</hi> let us <hi>flie</hi> to heaven; O Christians, let us <hi>flie</hi> to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven! <hi>Oh that I had wings like a dove; that I might flie away and be at rest,</hi> said holy <hi>David,</hi> Psal. 55. 6. and so I hear you say <hi>(me thinks)</hi> within your <hi>breasts.</hi> I would not live <hi>alwayes</hi> upon earth, if I might; truly no wise man would, for that were to be ever miserable, so saith my Text; and so will all say I presume that have heard me this day; <hi>If in this life only we have hope in Christ, we were of all men most miserable.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="eulogy">
               <head>The Eulogie.</head>
               <p>Having spoken thus far to the Text; give me leave to speak a few words to the occasion: The occasion of our meeting at this sad solemnity, is to do our last Christian office to this our deceased brother, <hi>William Christmas</hi> Esq in bringing his body decently to the grave. That body which was (not many days ago) the <hi>habitation</hi> of an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal <hi>soul,</hi> a <hi>member</hi> of <hi>Chrift,</hi> a <hi>temple</hi> of the <hi>holy Ghost,</hi> and is now carefully to be <hi>laid up,</hi> as a <hi>pledge of Hope,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til the Resurrection of the just. A grave and reverend <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> for his years having attained to the age of threescore and nine, and upwards, well nigh the compleat age of a man, according the <hi>Psalmist</hi>'s computation long ago: A grave and prudent <hi>Citizen,</hi> of this <hi>honourable City,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he was chosen (but fined) for the dignity of an <hi>Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of London,</hi> to the execution of which place, he was adjudged a man accomplished in all abilities, in all mens judgements, but in his own, who preferred a quiet privacy, before an honourable trouble. A grave and worthy <hi>Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> of the worshipful Company of the <hi>Drapers,</hi> wherein he went through the highest offices, with innocency and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. A grave and loving <hi>Inhabitant</hi> in this Parish, wherein for many years together he hath so behaved &amp; demeaned himself, that I must justly say, he neither lived unbeloved,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:120110:16"/> nor dyed unlamented. And now the <hi>box</hi> of his body is <hi>broken</hi> by death, his good name like <hi>pretious ointment,</hi> fils the place, with a <hi>sweet-smelling savour.</hi> A man religiously affected, and exprest himself such, both in publike and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate; diligent in businesse, prudent in counsel, punctual al in his promises, just in his dealings: a man very tender of his children, careful of his servants, hospitable at his ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, liberal to the poor; a man faithful to his friends, lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to his neighbours, and affable to all. It cannot rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonably be expected, that I should speak much of his life, which I can but take up upon trust, being in a manner a stranger to him; yet as little a stranger to him, as to any in this place, his very frequent and friendly invitations, and mine own duty obliging me often to visit him, whom <hi>God</hi> was pleased (soon after my reference to this place) by lamenesse and sicknesse (the summons to his death) to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine to his house. But those which knew him from his youth, to his dying-day, give a very fair testimony of him, as being a man of sound principles and constant to them; a legitimate son of the <hi>Church of England</hi> and no changeling; and that at last, upon private and intimate acquaintance, a grave <hi>Divine</hi> calling for an account of his <hi>hope,</hi> he made him an humble confession of his sins, and a sweet confession of his faith; with abundance of tears, as a holy water, distill'd from a heart, warmed with zeal and joy. Sure, he was one that loved our Nation, I mean the despised <hi>Clergie,</hi> and one that loved the <hi>Church, the house of prayer,</hi> that I observed often (almost as often as I saw him) it was his frequent and passionate wish, <hi>would to God I were able to go to Church with you,</hi> and <hi>I am sorry I cannot go to Church with you;</hi> as if he mist his legs upon no other terms, or for no other use so much, as to carry him to Church, as good <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> upon promise of his recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, said to the Prophet, <hi>what is the sign, that I shall go up to the house of the Lord?</hi> Before his death a good while,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:120110:17"/> he set his house in order, as well as his soul, and in his will forgat not the poor, the poor of this <hi>Parish,</hi> the poor of the <hi>Drapers Company,</hi> and the poor of <hi>Guildford</hi> where he was born; nor yet any of the <hi>Hospitals,</hi> or <hi>Prisons</hi> in and about <hi>London;</hi> besides other bounties, to his kinred, friends and servants. But a few dayes before his depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, I visited him, at which time, he gave a cheerful account of his Hope, and truly in such a manner, that I have rare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly met with a man, that upon humble and just grounds looked death in the face with more courage and Christian gallantry. In my necessary absence, his end approaching, and he sensible of it, he desired the <hi>holy Sacrament</hi> at the hands of a <hi>Reverend Divine,</hi> and received it, as the last <hi>viaticum,</hi> in the way to his <hi>Fathers</hi> house; which having cheerfully received, he earnestly wished, if <hi>God</hi> were so pleased, he might even now die; as old <hi>Simeon, now his eyes had seen his salvation,</hi> which pious wish, God was soon pleased to grant; for after a little patience and time, spent in prayers, counsel, and blessings on his Children, his memory and speech serving him perfectly to the last moment of his life; he only turned him aside on his pillow, and fell asleep; who is now (we hope) at rest, sweetly sleeping in the Lord Jesus.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:120110:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>